<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the city of London in Common-Councell assembled: to the Right Honourable the Lords &amp; Commons in Parliament assembled. Together, with the answers of both Houses to the said petition.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3547</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E443_35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872707</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125153</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125153)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E443[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the city of London in Common-Councell assembled: to the Right Honourable the Lords &amp; Commons in Parliament assembled. Together, with the answers of both Houses to the said petition.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Cotes Printer to the Honorable City of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The replies are dated 23. Maii, 1648.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125153:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HUMBLE PETITION OF THE Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons of the City of <hi>London</hi> in Common-Councell aſſembled: To the Right Honourable THE LORDS &amp; COMMONS IN <hi>Parliament Aſſembled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER,</hi> With the <hi>Anſwers</hi> of both Houſes to the ſaid PETITION.</p>
            <p>Printed by RICHARD COTES Printer to the Honorable City of LONDON, 1648</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:125153:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125153:2"/>
               <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE The Commons IN THE High Court of Parliament aſſembled: <hi>The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Commons of the City of London, in Common-councell aſſembled.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>SHEVVETH,</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat as your Petitioners in all humility doe thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge the many former favours of this honourable Houſe manifeſted to this City; ſo in particular
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125153:3"/>in granting their deſires, expreſſed in their late Petition, concerning the <hi>Tower</hi> and the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London:</hi> And in communicating unto the Petitioners ſeverall Votes of both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, wherein to your Petitioners great joy and comfort are expreſſed, your Reſolutions that you will not alter the Fundamentall Government of the Kingdome, by King, Lords, and Commons: That you will preſerve inviolably the Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the Treaties between the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> and that you will be ready to joyn with the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions agreed upon by both Kingdoms for the ſpeedy ſettlement of the Peace of both Kingdoms; and the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the union according to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Treaties.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:125153:3"/>
               <p>And your Petitioners doe further humbly preſent to this honourable Houſe, That the Inhabitants of the City are much grieved; in that their Magiſtrates and fellow-Citizens have for a long time been under reſtraint, and the City thereby deprived of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And humbly pray,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That in proſecution of your ſaid Votes, you will be pleaſed to improve all good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity in perfecting ſo deſirable a good as is therein expreſſed, for the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſettlement of the Peace of both Kingdomes, and preſervation of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion according to the Covenant and Treaties, and preventing a new and bloody Warre.</p>
                  <p>That the Aldermen now in the Tower, the Recorder, and the reſt of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens, reſtrained upon the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125153:4"/>occaſion may be diſcharged and reſtored, whereby the City may bee the better united, their hands ſtrengthened, and they made more ſerviceable to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and City for their preſervation and ſafety, which they ſhall endeavour to the uttermoſt of their power and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
               </q>
               <closer>And the Petitioners ſhall humbly pray, &amp;c.</closer>
            </div>
            <div n="lords" type="response">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:125153:4"/>
               <head>Die Martis, <hi>23.</hi> Maii, <hi>1648.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Lords have commanded me to let you know, That they receive the acknowledgments of gratitude, and the great expreſſions of fidelity and good affections from the City of <hi>London,</hi> with ſuch a ſatisfaction, as that they return you their hearty Thanks: They have commanded me to aſſure you, that they will improve all good opportunities for the attaining that deſired end of theſe unhappy troubles, the ſpeedy ſettlement of a ſafe peace in both Kingdomes, and the preſervation of the Union according to the Covenant and Treaties. They will endeavour to the utmoſt of their Power, to prevent any new and bloody Warre. As to the particulars mentioned concerning the Aldermen now in the Tower, the Recorder, and the reſt of the Citizens reſtrained: They have commanded me to declare to you, That they having had an Impeachment brought up from the Houſe of Commons againſt thoſe Aldermen, have proceeded no otherwiſe then by the uſuall courſe of Parliament they ought to have done. As to the Recorder, there hath been no Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or proceedings againſt him by this Houſe. As to the reſt of the Citizens againſt whom there is no Impeachment, but onely a Commitment by a Committee of both Houſes; their Lordſhips will proceed to endevour their ſpeedy releaſe. And they deſire that the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Common-Councell, and that the whole City may reſt confident, That their Lordſhips will uſe their endevours for their ſatisfaction: And as it hath alwayes been the ſtudy and labour of this Houſe to expreſs their Care for advantage and union of the City of <hi>London;</hi> ſo, much more now will they endevour a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with thoſe deſires of the City, which may firmly unite them one to another; and faſten their Hearts, and ſtrengthen their Hands in a ſerviceableneſs to the Parliament, in order to theſe ends, The eſtabliſhment of Religion, The peace and ſafety of the Kingdom, according to our ſolemn League and Covenant.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ioh. Brown Cleric. Parliamentorum.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="house" type="response">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:125153:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Die Martis,</hi> 23. Maii, 1648.</head>
               <p>THe Houſe being informed, That the Sheriffs, Aldermen, and other Citizens were at the door, they were called in, and Mr. Sheriff <hi>Bide,</hi> after ſome preamble by way of Introduction, acquainted the Houſe, That he was commanded by the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons in Common-councell aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, humbly to preſent to this Houſe, An humble Petition: The which the Petitioners being withdrawn, was read, and was Entituled,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Aldermen, and Commons of the City of London in Common-Councell aſſembled:</hi> In which they deſire the diſcharge of the Aldermen now in the Tower, the Recorder, and other their fellow-Citizens under reſtraint upon the ſame occaſion.</p>
               <p>The Sheriffs, Aldermen, and other Citizens the Petitioners, were again called in, and Mr. Speaker by the Command of the Houſe, acquainted them that the Houſe had conſidered their Petition, that in it are many deſires, which in the Petition are expreſſed, to tend very much to the union of the City in it ſelf, which how much this Houſe deſires, will appear by the Votes this Houſe hath paſſed upon their Petition. And then Mr. Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker acquainted them with the Votes concerning the Recorder, Colonell <hi>Bromfield,</hi> and other Citizens: As to the buſineſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Aldermen in the Tower; he informed them, that it is a buſineſſe of very ſerious and important conſideration: they have therefore reſolved to reſume the debate of it on this day ſeven night.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
